Guide to the Mark A. Bradley Collection on Duncan Chaplin Lee
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Mark A. Bradley collection on Duncan Chaplin Lee
1935-2013
MS 2063
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(7 boxes)
The collection comprises research materials compiled by Mark A. Bradley for his book A Very Principled Boy: The Life of Duncan Lee, Red Spy and Cold Warrior. Roughly half the material are copies of archival and government records along with related notes. Archival records include materials from personal papers kept at repositories such as the National Archives and the Hoover Institute. Government records are represented mainly from the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) and the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI). Government records have been mainly filed as part of Series I, Freedom of Information Act requests, but there are some intermixed with Series II, Research materials. There are also interviews with people who are related to Lee, studied with Lee, or worked with Lee. Lee's own writings about his work, family, and life are present, including a memorandum to his children about the Bentley affair. Finally, there are copies of several published articles that were used in Bradley's research. Materials date from 1935 to 2013.
Bradley, Mark A. (Mark Andrew), 1956-
Lee, Duncan Chaplin, 1913-1988
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series: I. Freedom of Information Act requests, 1942-2013. II. Research materials, 1935-2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mark A. Bradley, 2016.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises research materials compiled by Mark A. Bradley for his book A Very Principled Boy: The Life of Duncan Lee, Red Spy and Cold Warrior. Roughly half the material are copies of archival and government records along with related notes. Archival records include materials from personal papers kept at repositories such as the National Archives and the Hoover Institute. Government records are represented mainly from the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) and the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI). Government records have been mainly filed as part of Series I, Freedom of Information Act requests, but there are some intermixed with Series II, Research materials. There are also interviews with people who are related to Lee, studied with Lee, or worked with Lee. Lee's own writings about his work, family, and life are present, including a memorandum to his children about the Bentley affair. Finally, there are copies of several published articles that were used in Bradley's research. Materials date from 1935 to 2013.
Biographical / Historical
Duncan Chaplin Lee
Duncan Chaplin Lee was born on December 19, 1913 in Anqing, China. His parents served as missionaries in China and were from the United States. The family, which included a brother, Armistead, and a sister, Priscilla, moved back to the United States in 1927 and settled in Chatham, Virginia, near Lee's father's family. He attended Yale University and graduated in 1935. He was awarded a Rhodes Scholarship and finished his education at Christ Church, Oxford University. He received a B.A. in jurisprudence in 1937 and a Bachelor of Civil Law degree in 1938. He also was a Sterling Fellow at Yale Law School from 1938 to 1939.
Lee worked as a lawyer at Donavan, Leisure, Newton, and Irvine from 1939 to 1942. From there, he joined the newly created Office of Strategic Services (OSS), a predecessor to the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA). He was subsequently commissioned a First Lieutenant in the Army. Lee worked as an aid to the director, General William "Wild Bill" Donovan and over time became the chief of the Secret Intelligence Branch. The OSS was disbanded in 1945 and Lee went back to practicing law. His main work immediately after working for OSS was serving as counsel for the formation of the Civil Air Transport, a CIA backed project that airlifted supplies and troops to China, Taiwan, and Korea.
As a student at Oxford, he became interested in the ideas of the Communist Party. He saw it as a party that could stop the spread of fascism and joined the party as a secret member in 1939. It is believed that the Soviet Union recruited him as a spy shortly after joining the OSS. Over a period of three years he passed on political secrets to the Soviet government. When the war was concluded, former Soviet courier and operations assistant Elizabeth Bentley defected to the United States and implicated a number of Americans who served as sources. One of the sources she named when she testified to the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) on July 31, 1948 was Lee. Lee testified before HUAC denying the charges on August 10, 1948. He was believed due to a lack of written evidence to back up the charges, as well as his education and family background. When it was discovered in 1951 by the U.S. Army's Signal Intelligence Service's Venona Project that Lee was indeed a spy, the FBI was unable to press charges since the project materials were classified. Although he never faced any legal consequences, mounting questions about his trustworthiness from the accusations caused Lee to live outside of the United States from 1953 on. Lee died on April 15, 1988 in Toronto, Canada.
Mark A. Bradley
Mark Bradley was born in 1956. He is a former CIA analyst and is currently an attorney in the National Security Division of the United States Department of Justice. Lee earned his B.A. in history from Washington and Lee University, an M.A. in history from Christ Church College, Oxford University, and a J.D. from the University of Virginia.
Cold War; Espionage; Soviet Union; Bentley, Elizabeth; Bradley, Mark A. (Mark Andrew), 1956-; Lee, Duncan Chaplin, 1913-1988; United States. Central Intelligence Agency; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; United States. Office of Strategic Services; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Un-American Activities
- Freedom of Information Act requests, 1942-2013; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains records on Duncan Chaplin Lee that Bradley retrieved via Freedom of Information Act requests. Files from the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) and the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) focus on Lee's career in the OSS, background information about the OSS, and material about the Civil Air Transport. Files from the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the House Un-American Activities Committee, and the State Department cover different stages of investigation into Elizabeth Bentley's claims, Lee's espionage activities, and monitoring of his activities in the early to mid 1950s. Personal information in some of the records is redacted.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged by agency and alphabetically therein.
  - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)/Office of Strategic Services (OSS)
    - Declassified files, 1944-1945, 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Executive files, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Organization files on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1942-1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - History of the Office of Strategic Services booklet, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Civil Air Transport, clandestine services research, 1946-1960, 2009-2010 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI)
    - Elizabeth Bentley statement to the FBI, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Espionage files, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
    - Files on Duncan Lee, 1945-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4-7, Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - "Koch" cables, Project Venona files, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Report on Soviet espionage, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) declassified files on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1948, 2010-2013 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - State Department files on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
- Research materials, 1935-2012; Series II
  Series II contains government and organization records, interviews, research notes, and publications related to Lee's life and work. While there is some overlap between information present in Series I, Freedom of Information Act requests, this series focuses on a broader range of topics, including his time at Yale University, his time at Oxford University, recollections of his family, on people involved with his OSS and espionage activities, and general information about Project Venona, the Bentley testimony, and Civil Air Transport/Air America. Also present is Lee's memorandum to his children denying that he was a Soviet spy.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - "Elizabeth Bentley Matter" manuscript by Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Government and organization records
    - Christ Church, Oxford University, reports on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1935-1936 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Copy of Bentley statement with index, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - National Archives, requested records from General William Donavan Collection, 1943-1945 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Whiting Willaver Papers regarding Air America, 1952-1963, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Interviews
    - Espey, John, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lee, John, 2011-2012 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Petrie, Ishbel, regarding Elizabeth Bentley, 2000-2007 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Pforzheimer, Walter, regarding Watergate, 1999-06-17 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Scully, John, regarding Yale University, 1998-06-08 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Notes
    - Claire Chennault Papers regarding Air America, research notes, 2009 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Duncan Lee biographical background, 1984-2009 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Hayden Peake notes on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - John Haynes list of OSS spies, 2012 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Notes and copies from the Thomas Corcoran Papers, 1949-1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Notes and edits of Ishbel Petrie's "Not a Bowl of Cherries", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Rhodes Scholarship, records of Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Vassiliev's notes, Bentley's allegations against Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1944-1951 (Box 6, Folder 6-7)
    - Vassiliev's notes on "Koch", Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Otto Doering and headhunters in Burma taken by Duncan Lee, Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Publications
    - America Unbound: World War II and the Makings of a Superpower, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - "Bernard Schuster and Joseph Katz: KGB Spies in the United States", 2007 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - "Donavan Backs Duncan Lee as Loyal in the War," New York Herald Tribune, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Frank Cass Journals, "OSS and the Venona Decrypts", 1997 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Out of Bondage: KGB Target: Washington, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Perilous Missions: Civil Air Transport and CIA Covert Operations in Asia, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Project Venona pamphlets, Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Reader's Digest, Eric Sevareid article, 1944-02 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "Soviet Espionage at the Office of Strategic Services", Undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "Venona," Counter-Intelligence in World War II, National Counter-Intelligence Center, 2012 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "What the Spiders Did: U.S. and Soviet Counterintelligence before the Cold War", Undated (Box 7, Folder 6)